Philip Whalen Collection
© 2002 University of Connecticut
Philip Whalen Collection.
1958-1977.
Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Center.
University of Connecticut. Special Collections Department [Collector].
.15 linear feet.
Philip Whalen was born 20 October 1923, in Portland, OR. He has been a poet, novelist, lecturer, and instructor since 1951 and was ordained a Zen Buddhist priest in 1973. He became the head monk, Dharma Sangha, Santa Fe, NM, in 1984.
MSS19980218
Biography
Philip Whalen was born 20 October 1923, in Portland, OR, the son of Glenn Henry and Phyllis (Bush) Whalen. He attended Reed College (B.A., 1951) after having served in the U.S. Army Air Forces (1943-1946). He has been a poet, novelist, lecturer, and instructor since 1951 and was ordained a Zen Buddhist priest in 1973. He became the head monk, Dharma Sangha, Santa Fe, NM, in 1984.
He has received the Poets Foundation Award (1962), V. K. Ratcliff Award (1964), American Academy of Arts and Letters grant-in-aid (1965), Committee on Poetry grant (1968, 1970, 1971), and the Morton Dauwen Zabel Award from American Academy and Institute of Arts and Letters (1985) for "progressive, original and experimental tendencies."
Scope and Content
The collection contains a typescript of Whalen's Seven Newport Poems (1958), with textual variations from the published version, accompanied by a letter to Cid Corman (25 October 1958). Also included is a postcard from Whalen to Alan Marlowe (1975), letters to Whalen from Anne Waldman (1975-1977) and Clark Coolidge (1971-1977).
Related Material
Archives & Special Collections has a substantial collection of literary materials. Additional papers of Philip Whalen are in the papers of Bill Berkson, Larry Eigner, James Koller, Charles Olson and Ed Sanders, also located in Archives & Special Collections. For detailed information on these collections please contact the curator or ask at the reference desk.
For those interested in additional Whalen materials, selected programs involving readings performed at Naropa University have been digitized and are available here.
Index Terms
This record series is indexed under the following controlled access subject terms.
Persons:
Corman, Cid.; Coolidge, Clark, 1939- .; Marlowe, Alan; Waldman, Anne, 1945- .
Subjects:
Beat generation.; American poetry-20th century.
Document Types:
Correspondence.; Typescripts.
Occupations:
Poet.
Restrictions on Access
There are no access restrictions on this collection.
Acquisition Information
Items purchased from multiple vendors.
Detailed Description
- Correspondence,1971-1977
  - Coolidge, Clark, 1971 (Box 1:1)
  - Coolidge, Clark, 1975 (Box 1:2)
  - Coolidge, Clark, 1977 (Box 1:3)
  - Coolidge, Clark, 1977 (Box 1:4)
  - Waldman, Anne, 1975 (Box 1:5)
  - Waldman, Anne, 1975 (Box 1:6)
  - Waldman, Anne, 1976 (Box 1:7)
  - Waldman, Anne, 1977 (Box 1:8)
  - Waldman, Anne, 1977 (Box 1:9)
  - Waldman, Anne, 1977 (Box 1:10)
  - Whalen, Philip (to Alan Marlowe), 1975 (Box 1:11)
- Typescript,1958
  - "Seven Newport Poems", 1958 (Box 1:12)